  <chapter id="Hardware-Requirements"> 
    <title>Hardware Requirements</title>
     <para>The use of Scenic require specific hardware. Telepresence system oriented for realtime performance have to met certain standard, this for good reliability and performance. Our team is continuously testing various devices and computer parts. We frequently update this page with material that is adequate to use in a telepresence system. For any material that is not proposed in our list, please contact us. </para>
     <sect1 id="ComputerSpecifications"> 
     <title>Computer Specifications</title>
     We recommend the following computer specification: 

      <table>
          <title>High Performance Computer Specification</title>
          <tgroup cols="2">
              <tbody>
                  <row>
                      <entry>Computer Memory</entry>
                      <entry>4GB</entry>
                 </row>
                 <row>
                     <entry>Processor</entry>
                     <entry>Intel Core 2 Quad</entry>
                 </row>
                 <row>
                     <entry>Motherboard</entry>
                     <entry>Minimum of 2 PCI and 2 PCIe slot</entry>
                 </row>
              </tbody>
          </tgroup>
      </table>
      
      <table>
          <title>Medium Performance Computer Specification</title>
          <tgroup cols="2">
              <tbody>
                  <row>
                      <entry>Computer Memory</entry>
                      <entry>2GB</entry>
                 </row>
                 <row>
                     <entry>Processor</entry>
                     <entry>Intel Core 2 Quad</entry>
                 </row>
                 <row>
                     <entry>Motherboard</entry>
                     <entry>Minimum of 2 PCI and 2 PCIe slot</entry>
                 </row>
              </tbody>
          </tgroup>
      </table>

      <table>
          <title>Medium Performance Computer Specification</title>
          <tgroup cols="2">
              <tbody>
                  <row>
                      <entry>Computer Memory</entry>
                      <entry>2GB</entry>
                 </row>
                 <row>
                     <entry>Processor</entry>
                     <entry>Intel Dual Core</entry>
                 </row>
                 <row>
                     <entry>Motherboard</entry>
                     <entry>Minimum of 2 PCI and 2 PCIe slot</entry>
                 </row>
              </tbody>
          </tgroup>
      </table>
      
      </sect1>
    
      <sect1 id="VideoHardwareSpecifications"> 
      <title>Video Hardware Specifications</title>
        <sect2 id="GraphicCard">
        <title>Graphic Card </title>
        <para>The graphic card will manage your video output. The choice of your graphic card will depend on how you want to use Scenic. For now, we only support nvidia video card. Some ATI cards have problems with Xvideo extension. 
        Before choosing your graphic card, determine on wich linux distribution and releases you are.

Some graphic card may work only on certain releases. Before buying a graphic card, verify on the nvidia unix page that the hardware you are planning to use is supported not only by your linux distribution but also on the release you are using. 
        </para> 
        <table>
          <title>Graphic Card Specifications</title>
          <tgroup cols="2">
              <thead>
                  <row>
                      <entry>Video Output</entry>
                      <entry>Determine the number and type of video output required</entry>
                  </row>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                  <row>
                      <entry>VGA</entry>
                      <entry>The lowest common denominator that all PC graphics hardware supports</entry>
                 </row>
                 <row>
                     <entry>DVI</entry>
                     <entry></entry>
                 </row>
                 <row>
                     <entry>S-Video</entry>
                     <entry></entry>
                 </row>
                 <row>
                     <entry>HDMI</entry>
                     <entry>Not supported and not tested</entry>
                 </row>
              </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table>

        </sect2>
        <sect2 id="VideoCaptureCard">
        <title>Video Capture card</title>
        <para>     Here is a list of the video capture cards tested with Scenic:

Best Quality

Good quality

    Viewcast Osprey 100
    Viewcast Osprey 210
    Pinacle Dazzle AVC 100 (only in Ubuntu Karmic)

Medium Quality

    WintvHauppauge 350
    WintvHauppauge 1800

    NOTE: Choosing capture cards or DV

Capture cards have a few advantages over DV converters: they don't need additionnal converters, they are prone to less latency (typically always less than 60ms), you can manage multiple inputs through software and you can control image variables (brightness, contrast, etc). On the minus side, you need a PC with an available PCI slot. USB video capture devices are usually of domestic quality.

    If the PC has a Firewire (IEEE1394) interface, you can use a DV converter to get video. The quality and available features on these are quite varying. DV transmissioin is already (lightly) compressed, so videos have to be uncompressed first, then compressed again for transmission. This procedure adds a bit of latency (approximately 200ms). Image quality from a high end converter can be considered as good as that from capture cards. </para>

      </sect2>
      <sect2 id="Camera">
      <title>Camera and Camcorder</title>
      <para> USB, DV Point grey FL2G Sony XD-Cam EX1 Sony PD-170 Sony PDX-10
            Unibrain 
      
      </sect1>

      <sect1 id="AudioHardwareSpecification"> 
      <title>Audio Hardware Specifications</title>
      </sect1>
      
      <sect1 id="Network Specifications">
      <title>Network Specifications </title>
      </sect1>
        
 
  </chapter>
