<chapter id="network-test">
  <title>Network Testing</title>
  <para>The use of &app; require specific network capabilities. In
  this chapter we will determine what this capabilites are. We will
  also give you tools how tho evaluate and improve the quality of
  your network.</para>
  <sect1 id="network-requirements">
    <title>Network Requirements</title>
    <sect2 id="network-speed">
      <title>Network speed</title>
      <para>Network speed and performance are of the utmost
      importance. To ensure that the network can handle the &app;
      setup, system administrators / users must perform the tests,
      described below, on the local network and between two
      endpoints.</para>
      <para>The following performance rates must be met:</para>
      <para>Bandwidth: 3.5Mbps video + 1.6Mbps audio = &gt; 5Mbps +
      20%</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="network-bandwith">
      <title>Network bandwidth</title>
      <para>Network bandwidth is a measure of available or consumed
      data communication resources expressed in bits or multiples
      of it (kbps, Mbps etc). To determine the required level of
      needed bandwidth, you have to calculate the Mbps rate of the
      audio and video tracks (including compression rates).
      Example: a 3.5 Mbps MPEG4 video with 2 x 800kbps audio
      channels requires 5.1 Mbps. For best results, users should
      add to this a 20% leeway and also consider additional network
      usage such as chat, skype, web browsing and so on.</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="network-latency">
      <title>Network Latency</title>
      <para>Latency is the time taken for a sent packet of data to
      be received at the other end. It includes the time to encode
      the packet for transmission and transmit it, the time for
      that data to traverse the network equipment between the
      nodes, and the time to receive and decode the data. The
      degree of permissible latency depends on many factors. Users
      must first consider the scenic requirements; if for example,
      you only need to transmit sound one way without any form of
      interaction, then latency rates are somewhat irrelevant. As a
      rule, the latency rate should be scaled according to the
      distance between sites.</para>
      <para>Latency:30-200ms</para>
      <para>Approximate rates per average distance:</para>
      <para>Regional level: 30ms</para>
      <para />
      <para>Across the country: 75ms</para>
      <para />
      <para>Across continents: 200ms</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="minimum-jitter">
      <title>Jitter</title>
      <para>Jitter, in the context of computer networks, is a
      measure of the variability over time of the packet latency
      across a network. Packet jitter is expressed as an average of
      the deviation from the network mean latency (see above).
      Packet jitter is quite important as it can increase the
      overall rate of latency, it must therefore be taken into
      account in order to calculate the total latency. The average
      deviation from the network mean latency should be less than
      1%.</para>
      <para>Jitter: &lt;1%</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="minimum-packet-loss">
      <title>Packet Loss</title>
      <para>Packet loss occurs when one or more packets of data
      traveling across a computer network fail to reach their
      destination. Packet loss causes important signal distortions
      that are always noticeable, regardless of the packet loss
      percentage. In a worst case scenario, packet loss should
      never be higher than 1%. At levels higher than this, there
      will be a significantly noticeable impact on the quality of
      the image, and an highly disruptive impact on the quality of
      the audio transmission.</para>
      <para>&lt;1%</para>
      <para>&gt;1% = significant impact</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="local-network-test">
    <title>Local Network Testing</title>
    <para>You must download the debian sid iperf version 2.0.4-3 or
    2.0.4-4 on your desktop and install it on both computer. Double
    click on the package to start the Ubuntu package manager
    installation process.</para>
    <para>Test the two iperf sessions on a stable LAN. Here is a
    diagram of this first test:</para>
    <para>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="fig/network_testing_01.png"
          format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </para>
    <para>Connect the two computers to the same switch.</para>
    <para>Assign a static ip address to both computers. Follow the
    Ubuntu Networking for Basic and Advanced Users Tutorial and at
    the Network configuration menu, select Static IP Address and
    assign an IP address, ex: 192.168.2.168. Be sure to give a
    static IP address that does not conflict with your DHCP range.
    If in doubt, contact a system administrator.</para>
    <para>On one of the computers, open a terminal session
    (Applications/Accessories/Terminal), start an iperf server with
    the UDP option.</para>
    <para>
    <userinput>iperf -s -u -i 10</userinput>
    </para>
    <para>On the other computer, open a terminal session and start
    an iperf client with the UDP option.</para>
    <para>
    <userinput>iperf -c ''server ip address'' -u -b 1M</userinput>
    <cmdsynopsis>
   <command>iperf</command>
       <group>
      <arg>-s</arg>
      <arg>-c</arg>
      </group>

    </cmdsynopsis>
    </para>
    <para>The iperf report should be similar to this:</para>
    <programlisting>
    ------------------------------------------------------------
    Client connecting to 10.10.10.183, UDP port 5001 Sending 1470
    byte datagrams UDP buffer size: &#160; 108 KByte (default)
    ------------------------------------------------------------ [
    &#160;3] local 10.10.10.162 port 42451 connected with
    10.10.10.183 port 5000 [ ID] Interval &#160; &#160; &#160;
    Transfer &#160; &#160; Bandwidth [ &#160;3] &#160;0.0-10.0 sec
    &#160;1.19 MBytes &#160;1000 Kbits/sec [ &#160;3] Sent 852
    datagrams [ &#160;3] Server Report: [ &#160;3] &#160;0.0-10.0
    sec &#160;1.19 MBytes &#160;1000 Kbits/sec &#160;0.004 ms
    &#160; &#160;0/ &#160;852 (0%)
    ------------------------------------------------------
    </programlisting>
    <para>
    If the
    server reports 0% packet loss, then test your network with
    respectively 15M, 30M, 60M, 80M. If you detect packet loss,
    please refer to our troubleshooting section.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="bidirectional-network-test">
    <title>Bidirectional Local Network Testing</title>
    <para>This iperf bidirectional test evaluates network
    performances in the the context of bidirectional video and
    audio transmission.</para>
    <para>NOTE: For now we do not recommend the -d option in iperf
    as it generates unwanted warnings and errors.</para>
    <para>Single-sided bidirectional test:</para>
    <para>
    <userinput>iperf -c ''server ip address'' -b 30M -r -u</userinput>
    </para>
    <para>The -r option does a bidirectional test individually, you
    should get 0% packet loss on both sides.</para>
    <para>Simultaneous client/server test (on computers A and
    B):</para>
    <para>
    <userinput>iperf &#160;-s &#160;-u</userinput>
    </para>
    <para>On computers A and B, started at the same time, you
    should get 0% packet loss on both sides.</para>
    <para>
    <userinput>iperf &#160;-c ''server ip address'' -b 30M -u</userinput>
  </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="remote-network-test">
    <title>Remote Network Testing</title>
    <para>Perform a traceroute starting from your computer to the
    remote computer. This will show you the route taken by the
    packets across the network. You can use this to determine if
    the packets are traveling on the proper ISP.</para>
    <cmdsynopsis>
    <command>traceroute</command>
      <arg rep='repeat' choice='plain'><replaceable>host</replaceable></arg>
    </cmdsynopsis>
    <para>Now, repeat the same steps as the Local Network Test but
    this time between your local network and the remote
    network.</para>
    <para>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="fig/network_testing_02.png"
          format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="network-testing-tools">
    <title>Useful network testing tools</title>
    <sect2 id="ping">
      <title>Ping</title>
      <para>Ping will be used here to test the latency over the
      network.</para>
      <para>Open a terminal, by choosing the "Terminal" item from
      the Application:Accessories menu. Next, <userinput>ping -c 4 www.google.com</userinput>
      and press enter. The text content of the
      terminal should look like this:</para>
      <para>
      <programlisting>
PING www.l.google.com (74.125.93.104) 56(84) bytes of data.
64 bytes from qw-in-f104.google.com (74.125.93.104): icmp_seq=1 ttl=23 time=36.2 ms
64 bytes from qw-in-f104.google.com (74.125.93.104): icmp_seq=2 ttl=239 time=37.3 ms
64 bytes from qw-in-f104.google.com (74.125.93.104): icmp_seq=3 ttl=239 time=36.4 ms
64 bytes from qw-in-f104.google.com (74.125.93.104): icmp_seq=4 ttl=239 time=36.1 ms
--- www.l.google.com ping statistics ---
4 packets transmitted, 4 received, 0% packet loss, time 3003ms
rtt min/avg/max/mdev = 36.174/36.557/37.322/0.494 ms
</programlisting>
      </para>
      <para>Here we can observe that the average round trip time is
      36.557 millisecond with 0% of packet loss.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
