<glossary role="auto">
  <title>Scenic Glossary</title>
  <para>This glossary gives descriptions on various terms and words
  used in telepresence</para>
  <glossentry id="bandwith">
    <glossterm>Bandwidth</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>Network bandwidth is a measure of available or consumed
      data communication resources expressed in bits or multiples
      of it (kbps, Mbps etc).</para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  <glossentry id="jitter">
    <glossterm>Jitter</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>Jitter is the term used to express variation in
      latency. Jitter, in the context of computer networks, is a
      measure of the variability over time of the packet latency
      across a network. Packet jitter is expressed as an average of
      the deviation from the network mean latency (see above).
      Packet jitter is quite important as it can increase the
      overall rate of latency, it must therefore be taken into
      account in order to calculate the total latency. Jitter has a
      signifcant effect on the quality of video and audio
      streams.</para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  <glossentry id="latency">
    <glossterm>Latency</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>Latency refers to a period of delay (usually measured
      in milliseconds). This period of delay represent the time
      from the source sending a an information to the destination
      receiving it. In real-time system over a network there will
      always have latency. Scenic has been developed to minimize
      this latency but still, by example two musician playing over
      a network will always experience a delay between each
      other.</para> 
      <para>Latency is the time taken for a sent packet of data to
      be received at the other end. It includes the time to encode
      the packet for transmission and transmit it, the time for
      that data to traverse the network equipment between the
      nodes, and the time to receive and decode the data.</para>
      <para>We speak of one-way latency when we calculate the delay
      from A to B. We speak of round-trip latency when we calculate
      the delay from A to B and then back to A. Round-trip latency
      has a great impact in by example, the dynamics of a
      conversation, or in any interactive system that require
      retro-action on the given input. For regular voice
      interaction a latency of 250 ms round-trip can be notice by
      an user. Both in audio and video. For musician a latency of
      even 60 ms can be notice and disturb the user if he/she is
      not used to it..</para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  <glossentry id="packet-loss">
    <glossterm>Packet Loss</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>Packet loss occurs when one or more packets of data
      traveling across a computer network fail to reach their
      destination. Packet loss causes important signal distortions
      that are always noticeable, regardless of the packet loss
      percentage.</para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
</glossary>
