<chapter id="before-using-scenic">
  <title>Before Using &app;</title>
  <para>In this chapter, we will list a few things to think about
  when getting prepared to use &app; for a perfomance. First, we
  will list some recommended equipment. Next, we will describe some
  common setups. Next, we will give a summary on how to turn on the
  computer and test the network connection.</para>
  <sect1 id="equipment-list">
    <title>Equipment list</title>
    <para>This is a quick list of the equipement used for a basic setup. Note that you need equipement on both side (local and distant.)</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>One computer, for indications on what  kind of computer may be used, please refer to our <ulink url="http://svn.sat.qc.ca/trac/scenic/installation-manual/"> Installation Manual </ulink></para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>1 x video capture card supported under Linux.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>1 x sound card</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>1(+) video camera(s) with A/V output.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>1(+) set(s) of headphones.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>1(+) microphone(s).</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>1 x audio mixer with at least two audio subgroups, so
        you can have one mix for local output and one mix to
        send.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Ethernet connector (10/100).</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Network connection devices (hub, firewall,
        etc...).</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="common-setups">
    <title>Common Setups</title>
    <para>The following setup description are common ways to use &app;.</para>
  <sect2 id="standalone-setup">
    <title>Standalone Setup</title>
    <para>Here is an overview of a standalone setup.</para>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="fig/hardware_setup_01.jpg" format="JPG" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="point-to-point">
    <title>Point to point setup</title>
    <para>This kind of setup refer to the communication between two
    &app; systems, both connected on a research/high-bandwidth
    setup.</para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="unidirectional-setup">
    <title>Unidirectional setup</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="fig/unidirectional_setup.png" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="bidirectional-setup">
    <title>Bidirectional setup</title>
    <para>Two groups of performance artists located in two separate
    venues interact directly with each other using live audio and
    video transmission. The performance in Room 1 is captured
    through cameras and microphones and sent to be broadcast in
    Room 2 and vice versa.</para>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="fig/bidirectional_setup.png" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="connecting-devices">
    <title>Connecting the devices</title>
    <sect2 id="supported-devices">
      <title> Supported Devices </title>
      &app; is usually used with many audio, video and MIDI devices.
      <para>It is really important to verify that you have
      devices that are supported by &app; and more generally by <application> GNU/Linux</application>. Please refer to
      our 
      <ulink url="http://svn.sat.qc.ca/trac/miville/wiki/HardwareRequirements">
      Hardware Requirements</ulink> page to know more about supported devices.</para>
      <para>It is also necessary to make sure that all devices
      are properly configured and connected.</para>
      <para>Here is an overview of the various peripheral used in a
      &app; setup and what is important to keep in mind.</para>
    <sect3 id="audio-input">
      <title>Audio input</title>
      <para>The most common audio input is a microphone. This microphone
      is then connected to the input of an audio mixer and then to
      a sound card. This Sound card is then connected to the
      computer.</para>
    </sect3>"
    <sect3 id="audio-output">
      <title>Audio output</title>
      <para>The usual direct audio output is a speaker or
      headphones. Sometimes, there will be an audio mixer between the sound card and the actual speakers.</para>
    </sect3>
    <sect3 id="video-input">
      <title>Video Input</title>
      <para>The usual direct video input is a video camera. A video capture card must be used to capture a video signal if it is analog. Some USB Web camera are also supported by &app;.</para>
    </sect3>
    <sect3 id="vide-output">
      <title>Video Output</title>
      <para>The usual direct video output is a projection screen
      and an control monitor.</para>
    </sect3>
    <sect3 id="controll-devices">
      <title>Controll Devices</title>
      <para>Of course, it is easier to use a computer when it has those devices. keyboard, mouse, touch-screen, wii-mote, etc... Before using non regular controller, be shure that they  </para>
    </sect3>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="turning-on">
    <title>Turning on the computer and its devices</title>
    <para>With audio and video systems, the order used to powering
    up each device is very important.</para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Connect only the mouse, the keyboard and the control
        monitor.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Connect the network cable to the network 
        interface</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Verify that you have enough power to supply your
        hardware. We strongly recommend the use of an UPS to
        regulate your power.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Power up the computer.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Verify that you log in the appropriate user
        session.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Verify that you are using the realtime kernel:</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Type in a terminal</para>
        <para>uname -r</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>You should see the -rt extension: 2.6.24-26-rt If
        not, you have to restart the computer. At the beginning of
        the reboot, you will see a grub window, press ESC and then
        select the kernel with the -rt extension.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Now you can turn off the computer.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Connect all the audio and video device following our 
        <ulink url="http://svn.sat.qc.ca/trac/miville/wiki/Hardware%20Setup">
        Hardware Setup</ulink> page.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>While connecting the device, be aware that if you
        have two video output, you need to connect both of the
        output before powering up the computer again so that both
        devices are detected.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Next, configure and test your audio and video
        following our 
        <ulink url="http://svn.sat.qc.ca/trac/miville/wiki/TestAudiovisualInputOutput">
        TestAudiovisualInputOutput</ulink> page.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <para />
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="internet-connection">
    <title>Be reached from the Internet</title>
    <para>To stream with &app;, both peer must make sure their 
    computer are reachable for the other computer. That means each
    peer must be able to send data to the other peer. </para>
    <para>The easiest way to make this happen, is to have a public
    IP address, and all ports open to the Internet - with no 
    firewall. An other solution would be to use a VPN.</para>
    <para>If you are using behind a router, one thing that you 
    can do it to configure your router to forward specific ports 
    to the computer running &app;. The port forwarding must be
    done for both TCP/IP and UDP/IP on the port 17446, as well 
    as for the whole range of 10000 to at least 11000.</para>
    <para>The port 17446 is the communication port of &app;. 
    &app; allocates port number from 10000 and up for the 
    receiving streamers. </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="testing-devices">
    <title>Testing the Devices</title>
    <para>Before trying to do any live audio and video streaming,
    one should make sure his devices are properly pluged-in and
    that they are powered on. Sometimes, an audio capture card
    might be in the digital mode, while you would prefer to use its
    analog inputs. Likewise, a USB MIDI capture device might be
    disabled by a push button that is in the "off" position. Those
    things might be obvious, but they are a common source of
    problems.</para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="sound-server">
    <title>Lauching the <application>JACK</application> Audio Server</title>
    <para>If you want to stream audio, you must run the <application>JACK</application> audio
    server. There is a simple graphical user interface for <application>JACK</application>
    that is called <application>JACK Control</application>. 
    You can launch it by choosing the <menuchoice><guimenu>Application</guimenu><guimenuitem>Audio/Video</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>JACK Control</guimenuitem></menuchoice> menu item.</para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="launching-scenic">
    <title>Lauching &app;</title>
    <para>To launch &app;, choose the <menuchoice><guimenu>Application</guimenu><guimenuitem>Internet</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>&app;</guimenuitem></menuchoice> menu item. You should be ready to go!</para>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
