<chapter id="contact-settings">
<title>The Address Book</title>
<para>In this chapter, we will explain how to use the address book that is in Scenic. To invite a remote peer to stream with you, you must add its IP address in your address book. You can give it a name so that it is easy to know with who you are streaming. When this is in your address book, you can invite it.</para>
<sect1 id="add-delete-contact">
<title>Adding and Deleting Contacts</title>
<para>This section of the interface allows users to add, remove and configure contacts. You need to create a contact on both machine, remote and local. </para>
   <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
         <para>Add a new contact: to add a connection, click the button with the plus "+" sign. To remove a connection, click the button with the minus "-" sign. </para>
      </listitem>
   </orderedlist>
   <para>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="fig/click_on_add_contact.png" format="PNG" /> 
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </para>
   <para>Next, a dialog will appear with the appropriate contact field: </para>
   <para>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="fig/add_contact_edit_dialog.png" format="PNG" /> 
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </para>
   <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
         <para>Name: insert the name of your contact in the field Name:. </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
         <para>Address: insert the contact's IP address in the field IP Address:. </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
         <para>Auto Accept: check this option if you want to accept every invitations from the remote user. This will not ask you any confirmation each time. This can make things a lot easier when there is only one person that controls both sides. Beware that your privacy may be a concern, since when the Scenic application is running, this peer can start a streaming session, and look and listen at what is happening on your side.</para>
      </listitem>
   </orderedlist>
   <para>On the contact window, you can see a summary of the current settings for this particular contact. </para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="inviting-peer">
    <title>Inviting a remote peer to stream</title>
    <para>To invite a contact, simply click on its name in the address book and click on the "Invite" button.</para>
    <para>When one receives an invitation, a dialog appears, asking the user if he agrees to start a streaming session. If the user accepts, the streaming starts. This step can be skipped by enabling the "Auto accept" option for a contact, as described above.</para>
    </sect1>
</chapter>
