<chapter id="Introduction">
  <title>Introduction</title>
  <para>&app; is an on stage telepresence system that allows for
  real time transmission of audio, video and control data over any
  IP network. Telepresence systems can be used in various artistic
  contexts, so that two different creative spaces can communicate
  with each other or present a combined performance. &app; provides
  different performance schemes that allow a maximum number of
  users to participate in a network of learning, research and
  artistic creation anywhere in the world (bandwidth
  permitting).</para>
  <para>The &app; development project is a part of the SAT
  PropulseART research program that was created to facilitate the
  implementation of remote networking for audiovisual, stage and
  digital systems between cultural and educational venues and to
  promote research and creation through new communication
  technologies.</para>
  <sect1 is="art-direction">
    <title>Thinking About the Art Direction</title>
    <para>When preparing a show that includes live telepresence,
    there are thinkgs to consider that can help a lot to improve
    the general quality of the performance. First, live arts that
    involve the body as a whole are generally more interesting to
    look at than those in which the body is rather static, not
    moving. Next, planning many short numbers separated by the
    comments of a master of ceremony can help the public to figure
    out what is actually going on with the telepresence. Otherwise,
    newcomers might now understand at all that some of the images
    are steamed live from an other city.</para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="UsingScenic">
    <title>Using Scenic</title>
    <sect2 id="performance-issues">
        <title>Performance Issues</title>
        <para>When planning a show, it is important to consider the limitations that are inherent to the computers and hardware. For example, it is more efficient for a computer to output only a single video image, rather than many. This single image can be splitted with hardware splitters that introduce close to no latency to the system. This is valid for both digital and analog video signals. </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="audio-feedback">
        <title>Fighting Against Audio Feedback</title>
        <para>When sending and receiving audio signals in a context of telepresence, serious audio feedback can occur. The symptoms consist most often in very loud high-pitched tones. The quickest way to fix this is to turn off the microphones or the speakers. It is possible to take some precautions to avoid these undesirable problems.</para>
        <para>When planning the scenography for a show, the easiest way to avoid audio feedback is to use headphones for playing back the audio that is received from the remote peer. If not possible, one could consider using musical instruments that use pickups, rather than microphones. Otherwise, using very directional microphones, or some that have a very short range, can solve this issue. In any case, avoid directing the micrphones towards the speakers. </para>
        <para>To help fighting against audio feedback, you can plan to use a limiter, a gate or a compressor in your audio processing chain. Of course, this does not replace the hardware precautions listed above.</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="projections-and-lighting">
        <title>Video Projections and Lighting</title>
        <para>A few common issues are commonly encountered in shows involving both video projections and lighting. Of course, both consist in light, and are best seen in a dark environment, since that makes sures the light on dark ratio is at its most. Using both video and lighting at the same time increases the general brightness in the room which decreases the possible dynamic range of light and shade. When planning a show, one should locate the lights as far as possible from the video displays in avoid to avoid light spills on it.</para>
        <para>When lighting a subject to be captured by a video camera, it is best to light it well. That means lighting it enough, so that the camera does not need to add to the image a lot of gain, which decreases the image quality. That also means using a well-known technique, such as the three points lighting. This technique consists in a key light, a fill light and a back light. The fill light decreases the shadow created by the strong key light. The back light is useful for lighting the shoulders and head of the subject. That detaches it from the background. Two back lights can be used.</para>
        <para>Using a dark background can also help to make the image easier to recognize. The subject can be dressed up in light colours. That makes it easier to recognize.</para>
        <para>It is safe to think that a better image is easier for a computer to compress. That will result in a smaller bandwidth. The general rule is: garbage in, garbage out. Shoot nice images and the result is more likely to be neat.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
