<chapter id="video-settings">
  <title>Video Settings</title>
  <para>This chapter describes how to setup your video settings in
  Scenic. How course, Scenic can transmit video to a remote
  peer.</para>
  <para>Each peer configures its video capture size and chooses the
  right device. Next, when using analog capture device, the video
  standard can be PAL or NTSC.</para>
  <para>Scenic is designed so that configuring the video codec must
  be done by the receiver. This way, the receiver can fine tune the
  quality of the image it receives. On the receiver's side, the
  operator can also choose to display the window in full screen on
  a specific display. This is also where the user chooses the
  jitter buffer for the video stream. Increase it to prevent poor
  image quality in case of packets loss. Increasing the jitter
  buffer add mores latency, so it is better to have a sane network
  with close to no packets loss, instead of increasing this
  value.</para>
  <sect1 id="sending-video">
    <title>Sending Video</title>
    <para>In this section, it is possible to configure the video
    image that will be sent to your remote peer.</para>
    <sect2 id="video-preview">
      <title>Video Preview</title>
      <para>The preview option will show you the video you are
      actually capturing, (The one you will send to the receiver)
      This enable you to validate that you are actually capturing a
      video feed.</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="video-source">
      <title>Video Source</title>
      <para>Here you can choose witch video source you want to use
      to send. To make a color test, you can use the Color bars.
      Scenic detects which supported video devices are connected to
      your computer, and lists them there. It tries to detect them
      every tiem the user switches to the video tab, and when
      trying to initiate a streaming session with a peer. That
      means that if you don't see a video device you have just
      plugged, you could try switching to an other tab, and
      switching back to the video tab, to see if it is
      detected.</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="video-in">
      <title>Video Input</title>
      <para>Some devices have many input, such as S-Video,
      composite, etc. In this case, you must choose the input to
      which the camera is connected to.</para>
      <para>If using an analog video capture card, S-Video is
      generally preferable over a composite input, since it offers
      a better image quality, especially for colors. A component
      input is even better. S-Video is an analog video signal that
      carries video data as two separate signals: luma (luminance)
      and chroma (color). This differs from composite video, which
      carries picture information as a single lower-quality signal,
      and component video, which carries picture information as
      three separate higher-quality signals.</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="video-standard">
      <title>Video Standard</title>
      <para>When using an analog video capture card, this
      configuration entry must be set accordingly to the video
      standard of the camera. Most of the Americas, Japan, South
      Korea, Taiwan, Burma, and some Pacific island nations and
      territories use NTSC. The rest of the world use PAL</para>
      <para>PAL: Phase Alternate Line, is an analogue television
      encoding system used in broadcast television systems in large
      parts of the world. Many European country uses this standard.
      NTSC: National Television System Committee, is the analog
      television system used in most of North America, South
      America, Japan, South Korea, Taiwan, Burma, and some Pacific
      island nations and territories.</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="aspect-ratio">
      <title>Aspect Ratio</title>
      <para>The aspect ratio of an image is the ratio of the width
      of the image to its height. Scenic currently supports 4:3 and
      16:9. Finally, the aspect ratio can be 4:3 or 16:9, depending
      on if the image source provides square pixels or rectangle
      pixels. Commonly used values are 16:9 for 704x480 and 4:3 for
      640x480</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="image-size">
      <title>Image Size</title>
      <para>This drop-down menu offers you a list of image size to choose for the video image to capture. A bigger image needs more bandwidth if you want it to be too much compressed. </para>
      <para>Since the bandwidth is decided on the receiver's side, both peers should agree on an image size and quality to avoid getting an ugly image or using too much bandwidth for no reason.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="receiving-video">
    <title>Receiving Video</title>
    <para>In Scenic, each peer decides the quality of the video that he receives. This means choosing the video codec, the bitrate and the jitter buffer. It is also possible to choose to start the receiver in full screen, and to show it on a secondary display.</para>
    <sect2 id="video-codec">
      <title>Video Codec</title>
      <para>Choose h.263 for low bandwidth or low CPU setup. Use
      Theora for a patent-free experience. Use MPEG4 for most
      situation. Use h.264 to use all the CPU power you
      have.</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="video-bitrate">
      <title>Video Bitrate</title>
      <para>Video bitrate is the number of bits of video data that
      are conveyed or processed per unit of time. It is expressed
      in Mega bits per second. Video bitrate capabilities varies
      depending of the video codec used:</para>
      <para>video: high-bandwidth (H.264), medium-bw (MPEG-4),
      low-bw (H.263)</para>
      <informaltable frame="all">
        <tgroup cols="5">
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>Name</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>Codec</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>Minimum Bitrate</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>Maximum Bitrate</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>Notes</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>High-Bandwidth H.264 Video</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>h264</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>2 Mbps</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>16 Mbps, seems to be limited only by
                CPU</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>Most CPU-intensive (though scales to multiple
                cores) and most latency.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>Medium-Bandwidth MPEG-4 Video</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>mpeg4</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>100 kbps (will go to 500 kbps with
                motion)</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>4Mbps (generally will be stay at 3Mbps
                without a lot of motion)</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>Preferable tradeoff for CPU-cost + Latency
                vs. Quality.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>Low-Bandwidth H.263 Video</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>h263</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>500 kbps</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>4Mbps</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>Bitrate variable, depends largely on image
                source material. Doesn't like sudden, extreme
                changes in light (results in stuttering). Least
                CPU-intensive, lowest latency, reasonable quality
                at higher bitrate.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>Low-Bandwidth Theora Video</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>theora</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>videoquality=5</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>videoquality=45</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>Quality engine is much more reliable than
                using the bitrate setting. Tends to stutter with
                static, homogenous source material (i.e. camera
                pointed at wall) for low quality setting.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="fullscreen">
      <title>Fullscreen</title>
      <para>You have an option to automatically launch the
      receiver's window in fullscreen. Once the receiver's window
      is running, you can press the Escape (or F) key to toggle on
      and off the fullscreen mode.</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="x11-display">
      <title>X11 Display</title>
      <para>Useful to display the video on another monitor.</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="deinterlace">
      <title>Deinterlace</title>
      <para>Deinterlacing makes a nicer image when the source is
      analog, but it adds latency. You should never use it if the
      remote video source is a Web cam.</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="video-jitter-buffer">
      <title>Video Jitter Buffer</title>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
